[Music]
over the Christmas period I made this
which is peanut butter Bailey we're
going to turn that into gelato without
any additional sugar or
[Music]
whatsoever so using alcohol in ice cream
there's there's a couple of things to
note is
alcohol really affects the freezing
point of your ice cream gelato sway
whatever
but at the same time it's really
difficult to know what effect certain
alcohols will have so if you take a 40%
alcohol sew proper rum whiskies vodkas
that kind of thing they're all sitting
around the 40% or should be rum it
should be um but a lot of alcohol is
much lower than that such as Bailey's uh
you know there's a lot of rum lures or
Liquors that aren't rum at all all
they're just alcoholic mixes so you you
can't just kind of guess this it's like
dumping you know a rral or Stevia into a
recipe and just hoping for the best it
it doesn't work so what we're going to
do today is I'm going to show you how to
use Bailey which this is 177%
alcohol okay and turn it into a super
luxurious gelato but we're going to use
that Stevia
drops now Stevia drops great way of of
boosting a sweetness level without
affecting the freezing point and it's a
balance of solids this recipe is a bit
low in solids but anyway enough chitchat
let's just get on into it what are we
going to need for this recipe we are
going to need 357 G of milk I use 2% use
whatever milk you've got 58 G of skin
milk powder 330 G of your homemade
peanut butter Bailey's 1 and/ 12 G of
Gua gum or zanam gum and 3 G of stevia
drops now if you don't want to make the
peanut butter Bailey you can just use
normal Bailey but you are going to miss
some of the essential fats required
that's in the peanut butter that's in
here so if you do that you're going to
need to add some amount of cream my
neighbor really wants me to make a boozy
vanilla so I think probably next week
we're going to do a bourbon vanilla
which is going to be super nice anyway
357 of milk
330 of our peanut butter look at that
fat at the
top
330 we're going to do our skim M powder
in a little pot which is 58 g 1 and 1/2
G of gu gum the stabilizer is kind of
essential because uh because I'm not
adding any additional
sugar um
it's low in solids this recipe equates
to
31% solids but it's just about creating
a better mouth feel so that's what we're
doing we're just going to stir the GU
into our milk powder put that into there
whisk that together we going to put in
on hob not going to put our Stevia in
now we're going to just warm this up to
melt the fats together um get it a nice
homogeneous mix and then once it's
cooled down then we'll add this in so
let's get this on hob and get this
stirring we're not heating it up to any
temperature so let's just get it warmed
up 50° cenra something like that and
then we'll come back when it's done
right just a couple of minutes that's
all it takes just fire the heat up as
high as it will go and get it all mixed
together now we got a lovely creamy
looking ice cream base now that we're
safely off the
heat we're going to add in our Stevia
now don't just use Drops and and guess
cuz this is about 250 to 300 times
sweeter than normal sugar so it doesn't
take a lot to make it super sweet plus
it's kind of got a funky taste I think
so we want to kind of be careful so we
want three G of this so we're going to
get our little scales and we're going to
balance a spoon on top and that is
three
[Music]
G just get that all in
there weigh it how you will um but you
need those little tiny
scales so with our Stevia in there we're
going to just mix it back together one
last time before it goes in the fridge
not going to go in too long cuz it's not
that hot
now gu is a great stabilizer because it
has emulsification Tendencies too so it
not only does it stabilize but it also
emulsifies so it's a really nice easy
one for low temperature ice cream bases
so let's just get this in the fridge
it's only going to be in there for an
hour or two just to cool it right down
and then we'll get up and get it CH in
so once your ice cream base is chilled
down again it doesn't take long you're
going to take it out the fridge and just
give it a quick stir whilst our machine
is pre-chilling now we're going to pop
it in the machine get it ched up and
load into a container cuz we're just
going to pop that back in the freezer to
completely harden
off it's h us day oh 20 to 9 almost
and I really wanted some ice cream
[Music]
so so there we go the first introduction
into the alcoholic ice cream playlist
I'm going to do a lot of these um not
specifically cuz I'm an alcoholic but
you know I love alcohol and ice cream so
this is just a baby touch on using
alcohol in the next video in this series
we're going to go into depth we're going
to go into flavor combinations we're
going to go into how to reduce solids if
you're using alcohol we're going to go
into balancing with alcohol it's a whole
varied subject so make sure you like And
subscribe perfect texture super smooth
really
nice peanut butter flavor and the
aftertaste is the Irish whiskey coming
through in the peanut butter
Bailey's it's warm on the throat after
the actual ice cream has melted and
you've swallowed you're left with that
warming feeling in your throat which is
exactly what you want
for alcoholic ice cream anyway there's a
big company I think they're in New York
actually might be wrong Tipsy scoop this
is all they do alcoholic ice creams I've
not had it interestingly enough people
moan about ice cream being dished up
when it's too
liquid go and check out some of Tipsy
Scoops videos on social media look at
the consistency of the ice cream as it
comes out of the batch freezer it's
basically liquid still and this is
before we
finish this is the amount of alcohol
they put in there means their batch
freezers are really really struggling to
actually turn it into ice cream what
they do is they they batch it up into
their containers they get it in a super
blast
chiller and that brings that fruit that
temperature right down super super fast
and then it will freeze biggest problem
with that the most you take it out of
that blast chiller it's going to start
melting incredibly quickly so you you
need to be careful with alcohol in ice
cream cuz otherwise you're going to end
up with a pool of liquid in your bowl
rather than a scoop of ice cream anyway
enough rambling on this video I will see
you next week and and I will also see
you in episode two of alcoholic ice
creams
[Music]
w